Guide to the Osborn Family Papers 1832-1936 MS 474
© 2011 New-York Historical Society
Osborn Family Papers
1832-1936
MS 474
© 2011 New-York Historical Society
12.7 Linear feet (31 boxes)
The Osborn Family Papers consist of personal correspondence between members of the family (including forebears) of Henry Fairfield Osborn (1857-1935), paleontologist and for many years the head of the Museum of Natural History, as well as some of his professional correspondence and papers. Family correspondence spans the period from 1832 to 1936, and reflects the everyday affairs of several generations and branches of a prosperous New York family. The collection also includes journals and datebooks of Henry Fairfield Osborn and other family members.
Provenance
Purchase, 1972.
Access Restrictions
Open to qualified researchers. Portions of the collection that have been microfilmed will be brought to the researcher in that format and can be made available by Interlibrary loan. Researchers on site may print out unlimited copies from microfilm reader-printer machines at per-exposure rates. See guidelines in Reading Room for details. Photocopying undertaken by staff only. Limited to twenty exposures of stable, unbound material per day. (Researchers may not accrue unused copy amounts from previous days.) Items that include presidential signatures will be presented to researchers in duplicate form.
Arrangement Note
This collection is arranged in two series. Series I, Family Papers, includes correspondence and papers by and between family members, and includes Henry Fairfield Osborn's correspondence with his family and in-laws. Series II, Henry Fairfield Osborn Papers, consists of his non-family correspondence, primarily with professional colleagues and friends, and other professional and research papers.
Biographical/Historical Note
This collection includes personal papers and journals from Henry Fairfield Osborn ("HFO") and his family, forebears and descendants, encompassing several generations of the Sturges, Osborn and Perry families.
HFO's maternal grandfather, Jonathan Sturges (1802-1874), was born in Southport, Connecticut, and in 1821 joined the grocery business of Lumen Reed (1787-1836). Lumen Reed was a highly successful merchant who also assembled one of the earliest and most significant collections of American art. Sturges shared Reed's interest in the arts and became an important patron and collector of American artists in his own right. After Reed's death, Sturges led a group who bought his art collection, which was eventually donated to the New-York Historical Society.
In 1828, Sturges married Mary Pemberton Cady (1806-1894), also born in Connecticut. The Cady family moved to Fredericksburg when Mary was 12 years old, but returned to New York City in 1826. After their marriage, the couple lived in New York City, and had six children. In 1840, they built a country retreat in Fairfield, Connecticut, known as "The Cottage." Still standing, the house is one of the earliest example of American Gothic Revival architecture, and in 1994 was designated a National Historic Landmark.
Well-educated, cultured, and wealthy, the Sturges were connected with the artistic and commercial elite of New York, as described in Mary Sturges' memoir Reminiscences of a Long Life (also held in the N-YHS library). One daughter, Amelia, married Pierpont Morgan in 1861, but died of tuberculosis four months after their wedding. Their oldest daughter, Virginia Reed Sturges (1830-1902), married William Henry Osborn in 1858.
William Henry Osborn (1820-1894) was a railroad executive, becoming President of the Illinois Central Railroad in 1853, and later heading the Chicago, St. Louis and New Orleans Railroad. William and Virginia Osborn lived in a sumptuous mansion at 32 Park Avenue, and later also built a mansion known as Castle Rock in Garrison, New York, which served as the family's summer home. The Osborn's had four children, two of whom (Virginia and Frederick) died as young adults.
Their eldest surviving son, Henry Fairfield Osborn (1857-1935), became a famous paleontologist and served as director of the Museum of Natural History from 1908 to 1935, building the foundation for its outstanding fossil and dinosaur collection. Deeply religious, Osborn was a proponent of the now-discredited theory of orthogenesis to explain evolution, holding that an ill-defined guiding force shaped life from lesser to greater forms, and was also a firm believer in eugenics. These ideas, reflected in the collection, have tarnished Osborn's scientific and moral reputation with later generations.
Henry Fairfield Osborn married Lucretia Thatcher Perry ("Lulu," 1858-1930) in 1881. Lulu was the daughter of Brigadier General Alexander James Perry and Josephine Adams Perry; her sister, Josephine, married Junius Morgan in 1891. Henry and Lulu had five children, the youngest of whom died in infancy.
Scope and Contents Note
The Osborn Family Papers includes correspondence and journals from members of the Sturges, Osborn and Perry families, spanning the century from 1832 to 1936. The collection is primarily focused on Henry Fairfield Osborn, famed paleontologist and long-time director of the Museum of Natural History, but also includes correspondence of his grandparents (Jonathan Sturges and Mary Cady Sturges), parents (William Osborn and Virginia Sturges Osborn), wife (Lucretia Perry Osborn), children (Virginia, Perry, Fairfield Junior, and Josephine), and various other relatives and family friends. These well-pedigreed families moved in New York's elite circles and the papers reflect the daily life and concerns of privileged members of New York's society in the 19th and early 20th centuries.
The collection is organized into three series. Series I, Family papers, consists primarily of correspondence between several generations of family members. Letters relate news of family members and friends, discuss current events, and describe modes and incidents of travel, both domestic and abroad. Health and religion are also frequent topics.
Series I also includes Henry Fairfield Osborn's family correspondence with his parents and siblings, and with his wife Lucretia Perry Osborn, as well as their correspondence with their four surviving children. There are also several boxes of correspondence and clippings relating to Lulu Osborn's 1927 monograph Washington in His Own Words.
In addition to correspondence, Series I includes deeds and leases for family property, genealogical and biographical information, several folders of family ephemera and photographs (including visas and passports), and a few journals or diaries.
Series II, Henry Fairfield Osborn Papers, includes his non-family correspondence with professional associates and organizations. Frequent correspondents include fellow paleontologist and friend William Berryman Scott, and British evolutionary biologist Edward Bagnell Poulton. Series II also includes Henry Fairfield Osborn's journals/datebooks from 1899 to 1921, as well as a few earlier journals. These consist primarily of calendar-type entries detailing Osborn's professional activities as well as events in his personal life; there are also a few journals containing more extensive accounts of his travels and expeditions.
Series III, Transcriptions and oversize material, includes typed transcriptions of hand-written letters of Henry Fairfield Osborn to his father and brother, and to William Berryman Scott, along with transcriptions of a few diary excerpts. This series also includes some oversize ephemera and biographical notes.
Morgan, Amelia Sturges, 1840-1861; Morgan, J. Pierpont (John Pierpont), 1837-1913; Muir, John, 1838-1914; Osborn, Henry Fairfield, 1857-1935; Osborn, Lucretia Thatcher Perry, 1858-1930; Osborn, Virginia Sturges, 1830-1902; Osborn, William Church; Osborn, William Henry, 1820-1894; Poulton, Edward Bagnell, Sir, 1856-1943; Scott, William Berryman, 1858-1947; Sturges, Jonathan, 1802-1874; Sturges, Mary Pemberton Cady, 1806-1894; American Museum of Natural History.; Biology -- Study and teaching.; Clubs -- New York (State) -- New York; Colorado.; Columbia University.; Diaries.; Education.; Eugenics.; Evolution (Biology) -- Study and teaching.; Fairfield (Conn.); Garrison (N.Y.); Immigration opponents--United States; Letters (correspondence); New York (N.Y.); Paleontology -- Study and teaching.; Photographs.; Princeton University.; Putnam County (N.Y.); Wyoming.
- Series I: Family papers
  Scope and Contents Note
  This series consists primarily of correspondence spanning several generations of families related to Henry Fairfield Osborn.
  Materials are organized into five subseries. Subseries I.1, Correspondence of Sturges, Cady, Perry and Osborn family members, includes correspondence of HFO's maternal grandparents, Jonathan Sturges and Mary (Cady) Sturges; his parents, William Osborn and Virginia (Sturges) Osborn; and various other members of the Cady family. Henry Fairfield Osborn's personal correspondence with his wife, Lucretia ("Lulu") Perry Osborn, is also included, along with other Perry family correspondence, primarily between Lulu and her mother, Josephine Perry.
  Early correspondence between Jonathan and Mary Sturges describes transportation and travel, food, health and medical care in the 1830's.
  Cady family correspondence includes letters between Mary (Cady) Sturges and her mother Elizabeth Cady, her aunt Olive Cady, and her sister Elizabeth Cady (later Mrs. Hamilton Murray). Letters span the period from 1832 to 1888, and discuss family news, health and events of daily life.
  Correspondence of the children of Jonathan and Mary Sturges includes letters by and between Virginia Osborn's siblings and their families, including a letter from J.P. Morgan, who married Virginia's sister Amelia Sturges. Amelia died of tuberculosis shortly after their marriage, and Morgan's letter to Jonathan Sturges, written December 28, 1861, describes her critical condition.
  Of particular interest is a folder of letters between Mary Sturges and her Fredericksburg friend Jane Beale, who remained in Virginia during the Civil War. The letters were written after the war, and describe the difficulties the confederate Beale family endured during and after the conflict.
  Subseries I.2, Correspondence of Osborn family children, contains correspondence of HFO's four surviving children (Virginia, Perry, Fairfield Jr., and Josephine) from early childhood, when they were away at boarding school, to adulthood, and includes many letters from their travels abroad.
  Subseries I.3, Other family papers and photographs, includes genealogical and biographical information about the various families; a small number of business, and legal papers, including wills and deeds and leases for family property; several folders of ephemera and photographs, including a few of HFO on an expedition in Egypt; and passports and visas issued to Henry and Lulu Osborn in the 1920's and 1930's. This subseries also includes a poignant memorial album for HFO's sister Virginia Reed Osborn, who died when she was only 20 years old.
  Subseries I.4, Correspondence and clippings of Lucretia Perry Osborn, includes materials relating to Lulu Osborn's activities outside the family circle, including several boxes of correspondence and clippings, primarily concerning her 1927 monograph Washington in His Own Words.
  Subseries I.5, Journals, consists of bound journals, including an 1868 datebook of William Osborn (from Europe), several diaries and "common place books" of Virginia Osborn (1850-1851, 1871, 1875), and an 1883 journal of Lulu Perry.
  - Subseries I.1: Correspondence of Sturges, Cady, Perry and Osborn family members
    - Letters between Jonathan Sturges and Mary (Cady) Sturges, 1832-1837, undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Cady family correspondence, 1832-1883, undated (Box 1, Folder 2)
      Includes letters to and from Elizabeth Cady (mother of Mary Cady Sturges') and between her daughters
    - Correspondence of Mary (Cady) Sturges, 1851-1882, undated (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Letters from Jane Beale to Mary (Cady) Sturges, 1865-1882 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Sturges' family correspondence, 1854-1883, undated (Box 1, Folder 5)
      Includes letters to and from the children of Jonathan and Mary Sturges, and their spouses (including J.P. Morgan, who married Amelia Sturges).
    - Other family correspondence; unidentified correspondents, 1858-1885, undated (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Family correspondence of Virginia Osborn, 1860-1884, undated (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - General correspondence of Virginia and William Osborn, 1869-1899, undated (Box 2, Folder 1)
      Includes letters from Frederic Church (one illustrated), his wife Isabel, and Worthington Wittredge
    - Letters from Virginia Osborn to Henry Fairfield Osborn, 1873-1883 (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - Letters from Virginia Osborn to Henry Fairfield Osborn, 1884-1901 (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - Letters from Virginia Osborn to Henry Fairfield Osborn, undated (Box 2, Folder 4)
    - Correspondence of William Osborn and Henry Fairfield Osborn, 1863-1900, undated (Box 2, Folder 5)
    - Letters from Henry Fairfield Osborn to William Henry Osborn and Virginia Osborn, 1875-1896, undated (Box 3, Folder 1)
      Related Archival Materials Note
      For transcriptions of some of Henry Fairfield Osborn's letters to his parents, see Box 30, Folder 1.
    - Correspondence of Henry Fairfield Osborn and other family members; other early letters of Henry Fairfield Osborn, 1871-1911, undated (Box 3, Folder 2)
      For transcriptions of some of Henry Fairfield Osborn's letters to his brother William Church Osborn, see Box 30, Folder 2.
    - Letters from Virginia Osborn to Lulu (Perry) Osborn, 1879-1891 (Box 3, Folder 3)
    - Letters from Virginia Osborn to Lulu (Perry) Osborn, 1893-1901 (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - Letters from Virginia Osborn to Lulu (Perry) Osborn, undated (Box 3, Folder 5-6)
      Some letters refer to Frederic Church and Olana.
      Also includes one letter from Jonathan Sturges to Lulu Perry.
    - Letters from Josephine Adams Perry to Lulu (Perry) Osborn, 1883-1887 (Box 4, Folder 1)
    - Letters from Josephine Adams Perry to Lulu (Perry) Osborn, 1888-1919 (Box 4, Folder 3)
    - Letters from Josephine Adams Perry to Lulu (Perry) Osborn, undated (Box 4, Folder 3)
    - Letters from Josephine Adams Perry to Lulu (Perry) Osborn, undated (Box 4, Folder 4)
    - Letters from Alexander James Perry to Lulu (Perry) Osborn, 1876-1888, undated (Box 4, Folder 3)
    - Letters from Josephine Adams Perry to Henry Fairfield Osborn; other Perry family correspondence, 1881-1887, undated (Box 4, Folder 5)
    - Letters from Lulu (Perry) Osborn to Josephine Adams Perry and Virginia Osborn, 1857, 1896, undated (Box 4, Folder 6)
    - Letters from Henry Fairfield Osborn to Lulu Osborn, 1881 January - April (Box 5, Folder 1)
    - Letters from Henry Fairfield Osborn to Lulu Osborn, 1881 May (Box 5, Folder 2)
    - Letters from Henry Fairfield Osborn to Lulu Osborn, 1881 July - December (Box 5, Folder 3)
    - Letters from Henry Fairfield Osborn to Lulu Osborn, 1882 - 1885 (Box 5, Folder 4)
    - Letters from Henry Fairfield Osborn to Lulu Osborn, 1886-1889 (Box 5, Folder 5)
    - Letters from Henry Fairfield Osborn to Lulu Osborn, 1890-1893 (Box 5, Folder 6)
    - Letters from Henry Fairfield Osborn to Lulu Osborn (Box 5, Folder 7)
    - Letters from Henry Fairfield Osborn to Lulu Osborn, 1894-1901 (Box 6, Folder 1)
    - Letters from Henry Fairfield Osborn to Lulu Osborn, 1902-1904 (Box 6, Folder 2)
    - Letters from Henry Fairfield Osborn to Lulu Osborn, 1906-1907 (Box 6, Folder 3)
    - Letters from Henry Fairfield Osborn to Lulu Osborn, 1908-1912 (Box 6, Folder 4)
    - Letters from Henry Fairfield Osborn to Lulu Osborn, 1913-1916, 1920-1927 (Box 6, Folder 5)
    - Letters from Henry Fairfield Osborn to Lulu Osborn, undated (Box 6, Folder 6-7)
    - Letters from Henry Fairfield Osborn to Lulu Osborn, undated (Box 7, Folder 1-3)
    - Letters from Lulu Osborn to Henry Fairfield Osborn, 1881 (Box 7, Folder 4)
    - Letters from Lulu Osborn to Henry Fairfield Osborn, 1882-1889 (Box 7, Folder 5)
    - Letters from Lulu Osborn to Henry Fairfield Osborn, 1890-1893 (Box 7, Folder 6)
    - Letters from Lulu Osborn to Henry Fairfield Osborn, 1894-1918 (Box 7, Folder 7)
    - Letters from Lulu Osborn to Henry Fairfield Osborn, undated (Box 8, Folder 1-7)
    - General correspondence of Lulu Osborn, 1875-1922 (Box 8A, Folder 1)
    - General correspondence of Lulu Osborn, 1923-1929 (Box 8A, Folder 2)
    - General correspondence of Lulu Osborn, undated (Box 8A, Folder 3)
  - Subseries I.2: Correspondence of Osborn family children
    - Correspondence of Virginia Osborn (daughter), 1885-1900 (Box 9, Folder 1)
    - Correspondence of Virginia Osborn (daughter), 1901-1904 (Box 9, Folder 2)
    - Correspondence of Virginia Osborn (daughter), 1905=1926 (Box 9, Folder 3)
    - Correspondence of Virginia Osborn (daughter), undated (Box 9, Folder 4-5)
    - Correspondence of Virginia Osborn (daughter), undated (Box 10, Folder 1-3)
    - Correspondence of A. Perry Osborn (son), 1897-1932, undated (Box 10, Folder 4)
    - Correspondence, Henry Fairfield Osborn, Jr. (son), 1890-1903 (Box 10, Folder 5)
    - Correspondence, Henry Fairfield Osborn, Jr. (son), 1905-1928 (Box 10, Folder 6)
    - Correspondence, Henry Fairfield Osborn, Jr. (son), undated (Box 11, Folder 1-3)
    - Correspondence, Josephine Osborn (daughter), 1896-1907 (Box 11, Folder 4)
    - Correspondence, Josephine Osborn (daughter), 1907-1908 (Box 11, Folder 5)
    - Correspondence, Josephine Osborn (daughter), 1908-1921 (Box 12, Folder 1)
    - Correspondence, Josephine Osborn (daughter), 1926-1932 (Box 12, Folder 2)
    - Correspondence, Josephine Osborn (daughter), undated (Box 12, Folder 5)
    - Correspondence "P.W." (friend of family?), undated (Box 12, Folder 6)
    - Correspondence and ephemera relating to education of Henry Fairfield Osborn's grandchildren, 1932-1935 (Box 12, Folder 7)
  - Subseries I.3: Other family papers and photographs
    - Deeds and mortgages, 1818-1897 (Box 13, Folder 1)
    - Business papers, William Henry Osborn, 1870's (Box 13, Folder 2)
    - Checks, American Exchange National Bank, 1880's (Box 13, Folder 2)
    - Estate and wills, William Henry Osborn and Virginia Osborn, 1868-1895 (Box 13, Folder 3)
    - Biographical materials, William Henry Osborn, 1920's-1930's, undated (Box 13, Folder 4)
    - Biographical materials, William Henry Osborn (Box 30, Folder 7)
    - Biographical materials and tributes, Virginia Osborn, 1910-1914 (Box 13, Folder 5)
    - Memberships and charitable work, Virginia Osborn, 1903-1928 (Box 13, Folder 6)
      Includes material relating to the Training School for Nurses, Army Relief Society, New York Cooking School, and New York Philharmonic
    - Genealogical and biographical materials, Sturges family, 1894-1922 (Box 13, Folder 7)
    - Program for dinner in honor of Jonathan Sturges; Poem dedicated to Mary (Cady) Sturges, 1868, 1886 (Box 14, Folder 1)
    - Genealogical and biographical materials, Perry family (Box 14, Folder 2)
    - Genealogical and biographical materials, Osborn family (Box 14, Folder 3-4)
    - Histories of Fairfield, Connecticut, by Henry Fairfield Osborn and Henry Sturges, 1910, 1935 (Box 14, Folder 5)
    - Passports and visas, Henry Fairfield Osborn and Lulu Osborn, 1920's-1930's (Box 14, Folder 6)
    - Assorted ephemera (includes calling cards, baptism cards, Christmas cards, programs, and other materials) (Box 14, Folder 7-8)
    - Memorial scrapbook of materials relating to HFO's sister Virginia Sturges Osborn (1854-1874), circa 1875 (Box 31, Folder 3)
      Includes condolence letters, reminescences, a lock of hair and a childhood photograph.
    - Lantern slides from lecture on Fairfield, Connecticut, undated (Box 15)
    - Film reel labeled "Garrison 1932" (Box 15)
    - Photographs of Henry Fairfield Osborn and associates, 1877, 1907, 1913, 1921, undated (Box 15, Folder 1)
      Includes lock of hair and baby photo of HFO, as well as photos from various trips and expeditions.
    - Photographs of family members and others; unidentified photographs, undated (Box 15, Folder 2)
    - Requests for photographs and related correspondence, 1920's-1930's (Box 15, Folder 3-4)
  - Subseries I.4: Correspondence and clippings of Lucretia Perry Osborn
    - Correspondence with Charles Scribner's Sons Publishers, 1927-1928 (Box 16, Folder 1)
    - Correspondence regarding book research, 1922-1929 (Box 16, Folder 2)
    - Letters acknowledging receipt of book, 1928 (Box 16, Folder 3)
    - Ephemera relating to book research (publications, pamphlets, event flyers) (Box 16, Folder 4-6)
    - Research notes (Box 16, Folder 7)
    - Articles and other writings of Lulu Perry, undated (Box 16, Folder 8)
    - News clippings: reviews, 1928 (Box 17, Folder 1)
    - News clippings: research (Box 17, Folder 2-3)
    - Miscellaneous news clippings and poetry (Box 17, Folder 4)
    - Miscellaneous news clippings and poetry (Box 18, Folder 1)
    - Clippings and pamphlets relating to Great Britain/WWI, 1910's-1920's (Box 18, Folder 2)
  - Subseries I.5: Journals
    - Date book, William Osborn, 1868 (Box 18, Volume 1)
    - Journal, Virginia Osborn, 1851 (Box 18, Volume 2)
    - Journal, Virginia Osborn, 1871 (Box 18, Volume 3)
    - Journal, Virginia Osborn, 1875 (Box 18, Volume 4)
    - Commonplace book (school), Virginia Osborn, 1844 (Box 18, Volume 5)
    - Commonplace book (school), Virginia Osborn, undated (Box 18, Volume 6)
    - Religious journal, Virginia Osborn (notes for Bible School?), 1876 (Box 18, Volume 7)
    - Journal, Lulu Perry, 1883 (Box 17, Volume 8)
    - "Recollections of a Happy Life" by Elizabeth Christophers Hobson, 1916 (Box 18, Volume 9)
      Includes references to Virginia Osborn, a friend of the author
    - Extra pages of "Recollections of a Happy Life" (Box 18, Folder 3)
- Series II: Henry Fairfield Osborn papers
  Series II, Henry Fairfield Osborn papers, is organized into five subseries. (Note that this Series does not include the family correspondence of Henry Fairfield Osborn, which is found in Series I, Family Papers.)
  Subseries II.1, Correspondence and related materials, includes HFO's non-family correspondence, primarily with professional colleagues and scientist friends. The most frequent correspondent is HFO's Princeton classmate and fellow paleontologist William Berryman Scott. Their letters (foldered separately) discuss both personal news and professional matters.
  The remaining correspondence is foldered chronologically, and includes frequent letters between HFO and British evolutionary biologist Sir Edward B. Poulton. Other notable correspondents include Howard Crosby Butler, Charles F. Dawes, Seth Low, John Muir, John Stewart Kingsley, and Edith Roosevelt. Topics include professional research, publications and speaking engagements, and news about colleagues and friends.
  Subseries II.2, Associations and honors, includes correspondence and other papers relating to HFO's numerous memberships in professional and social organizations and clubs, and his many honorary degrees, medals and decorations. Notable memberships include several organizations that promoted eugenics and/or racial purity, including the American Eugenics Society, the American Genetic Association, the Aryan Society, and the Galton Society. HFO was also a member of the exclusive Zodiac Club, along with J.P. Morgan, and this subseries includes invitations to dinners and other Zodiac Club correspondence. There are also several folders of correspondence relating to alumni events at Princeton. In addition, there is material relating to tributes in honor of HFO's birthdays, his retirement from AMNH and various other occasions.